Antarctica.
南极
The earth's coldest continent,
地球上最寒冷地方
the one that is most hostile to life.
极度不适合生物生存
Here, 800 miles from the South Pole,
这里，距离南极点800英里
it's 40 degrees below zero.
零下40摄氏度
Of all the millions of species of animals on Earth,
地球上数百万种动物中
only one can live here permanently.
只有一种能一直在此生存
A Weddell seal.
威德尔海豹
She can survive because she can dive below the ice.
它能生存是因为可以潜到冰层下面
Here she is protected from the storms above,
使自己不受上面的暴风雪袭击
and here too, she can find food.
这里也能找到食物
But she is a mammal,and she has to breathe air,
但它是哺乳动物，必须呼吸空气
so she has to keep a lifeline open to the world above the ice.
所以它必须守住一条通到冰层上面的生命线
Not only for her,
不只是为自己
but now for her newborn pup.
也为刚出生的幼仔
He's less than a week old, and still very vulnerable.
它还没一周大，仍旧很脆弱
A blizzard blows in, and with it, storm-force winds.
暴风雪来袭，力量强劲
It could last for a week.
可以持续一周
Being mammals, seals can generate heat within their bodies.
作为哺乳类，海豹可以体内产热
And their fur, with a thick layer of fat beneath it,
皮毛下面是一层厚厚的脂肪
prevents most of that heat from escaping,
能防止绝大多数的热量散失
even in cold conditions like this.
即便是在这么冷的情况下
What is more,she is able to feed her youngster
更重要的是，它能用哺乳动物所特有的
with that mammalian speciality,milk.
乳汁，来哺育后代
And while she does so, she shields him from the worst of the blizzard.
哺乳时，它还为幼仔遮挡住暴风雪
She has worked hard throughout the winter to prevent her breathing hole
整个冬天，它都孜孜不倦地工作
in the ice from freezing over.
防止通气孔被冰冻封住
That requires constant attention -
这需要持久的专注
filing back the edges of the hole with her teeth.
用牙齿清除洞周围的冰
Her pup needs to join her under the ice as soon as he can swim properly.
一旦幼仔长到适合游泳，就得跟它一起下水
She encourages him to take his first plunge, but,
它鼓励它第一次下水
hardly surprisingly, he is not keen.
奇怪的是，它一点也不紧张
Now, guided by his mother, he has to learn how to hunt underwater,
现在，在妈妈的指导下，它要学习如何在水下捕食
and to find his way back through the maze to his hole in the ice.
同时能够在水下迷宫里找到返回通气孔的路
A warm body, fur, milk and maternal care are essential
体温、皮毛、乳汁以及母亲的呵护
for the Weddell seal's survival in this freezing environment.
是海豹在这严寒里生存必不可少的
And those qualities have helped the mammals
这些特点有助哺乳动物
to colonise the entire globe.
统治整个地球
Equatorial East Africa.
东非赤道地带
It's hard to image a place more different from Antarctica.
是一个与南极洲完全不同的世界
To survive here,mammals need additional talents.
要在这里生存，哺乳类需要额外的智慧
This tree shelters the territory of a tiny mammal
这三个窝点是一种小动物的领地
that spends its whole life in frenzied activity.
花费了它毕生的精力辛勤打理
It used to be called an elephant shrew,
以前被称作长鼻
but now it's called by its African name of sengi.
现在有个非洲化的名字：森吉（扎伊尔硬币）
This is a female rufous sengi.
这是一只红褐色的雌性sengi
And, like all sengis, she's so active, she's permanently hungry.
就像所有的sengi一样，它太活跃，总是吃不饱
To get all the food she needs,
为了得到足够的食物
she has to be both industrious and ingenious.
它必须勤劳而又灵巧
She has made an intricate network of trails
它为设计了错综复杂的路线
that enable her to hunt her insect prey very efficiently.
帮助自己有效地猎食昆虫
But these pathways have another important function
但这些通道在遭遇天敌时
when she meets her enemies.
有重要的作用
Having a map of these trails in her head can mean the difference
能否在头脑中牢记这张路线图关系着
between life...
生存
..and death.
或死亡
Like most mammals,and unlike reptiles,
跟爬行类不同，像大多数哺乳类
her legs are directly beneath her body.
它的腿长在身体正下方（爬行类在身体两侧）
That makes her less stable, but much faster and more agile.
这使它不太稳定，但是更加迅速灵巧
Not only has she outrun this reptile, she's outwitted him.
它不但比这只蜥蜴跑得快，更比它聪明
And just as well,
还有
for she is a mother and has a youngster to care for.
它是一位需要照顾幼仔的母亲
The sengi relies on speed and cunning for its success.
sengi依靠速度和智谋取得成功
Other mammals have very different techniques.
其它的哺乳类有不同的技能
Here in Madagascar,
马达加斯加
one of the most bizarre of all mammals is on the prowl.
一种最为怪异的哺乳动物正在游荡
The aye-aye, like the sengi,lives on insects.
长指狐猴，跟sengi一样，吃昆虫
But the ones that she seeks,she can't see,
但它看不见所找的食物
for they're buried deep inside branches.
因为它们躲在树干深处
They're beetle grubs.
它们是挖虫高手
To find them,she has a special talent.
为找到食物，它有特殊天分
She taps her fingers on the wood up to eight times a second,
它用手指以每秒8次的速度敲击树干
and listens for the tiny change in resonance
通过分辨回声中的细微差别
that indicates a hollow spot within.
侦测出里面是否有洞
Her hearing is so acute, she can identify the precise position
它的听力及其灵敏，能准确定位
in which to gnaw a hole in order to reach the grub.
然后咬开树皮，找到虫子
And she has a grotesquely long middle finger
用它变态的超长中指
with which to skewer it.
刺入洞中抓虫
It takes a young aye-aye four years to perfect this technique.
长指狐猴要花费四年时间来完善这种技能
But once it has done so,
一旦练成
it can collect prey that no other mammal can reach.
它就能得到别人吃不到的食物
The Arctic tundra.
北极冻原
Food is hard to find here too.
这里也很难找到食物
Indeed, this land is so barren that few large animals can live here.
实际上，这片土地太过贫瘠，极少有大型动物能在这里生存
Yet one mammal has found a way to do so.
但有一种哺乳动物可以做到
It's late spring,
晚春
and as the mounting strength of the sun warms the land,
太阳温暖大地
eight million reindeer move north.
约8百万只驯鹿向北迁移
But the vegetation is so meagre
但是草木太过稀少
that the only way the herds can get enough
鹿群想要吃饱，就必须
is to keep constantly on the move.
一路吃下去
Newborn calves soon discover
新生小鹿很快就发觉
that they will have to spend every day walking in search of food.
它们必须每天赶路找吃的
They have extraordinary endurance.
它们有着惊人的耐受力
Some of these animals,before they die,
这种动物在死之前
will have trekked for a distance
已经走了很长的路
equivalent to three times around the earth.
足够绕地球三周
Grazing is now at its best.
现在的牧场是最好的
But this also the time when the reindeer' worst enemy appears...
但驯鹿们最讨厌的敌人,也在此时现身
Biting flies.
吸血蝇
The flies not only drive them to distraction,
苍蝇不但扰得它们心烦意乱
but they can drain a pint of blood each day.
而且每天可以吸掉它们一品脱的血
But the reindeer have a defensive strategy.
驯鹿们有一种防御策略
Each individual tries to push its way into the centre of a group
每一只都尽力朝群体中心靠拢
where there are fewer flies.
在那里苍蝇很少
With all this pushing and jostling,
所有的鹿挤在一起
mothers need to keep their calves close.
母亲们必须盯紧自己的孩子
Sometimes the flies become so bad
有时候苍蝇太过分了
the reindeer can stand them no longer
鹿群实在无法忍受
and they bolt to higher ground where the flies can't follow.
它们都逃向苍蝇们无法跟随的高地
But the price of escape can be high.
但这种逃避也有代价
In the rush,one mother has lost her calf.
慌乱中，一个鹿妈妈丢失了她的孩子
Others have already found it.
已经被别的生物找到了
The herd has long since moved on,
鹿群照旧前进
but her maternal instinct is so strong
但它母性本能十分强烈
she'll stay to search for her missing calf for days.
它会留下来好几天，寻找丢失的孩子
The reindeer are free from flies for now,
鹿群现在摆脱了苍蝇的困扰
but with no food on these high slopes,
但在这高山上没有食物
they will eventually be forced to descend to find new pastures
它们将会被迫下山寻找草场
and face the biting swarms once more.
再一次面对吸血蝇
No animal makes a longer migration across the lands of the earth
地球上没有哪种动物比它们
than these mammals.
迁徙的更远了
Other mammals have found a more economic way
有些生物找到了一种更经济的方式
of travelling huge distances and at greater speed.
进行更快速的远距离迁徙
They go by air.
它们用飞的
Giant straw-coloured fruit bats
巨大的食果黄蝙蝠
inhabit the great forests of the Congo.
栖居于刚果森林
Their wings are nearly a metre across.
它们的翼展达一米
In late October every year,
每年十月下旬
they set off on a long journey across the forest canopy.
它们动身越过森林，进行长途旅行
Flocks of hundreds become thousands.
从几百只到几千只
And tens of thousands become hundreds of thousands.
然后几万、几十万
They are fast and powerful fliers
它们是快速而强健的飞行家
and can travel a thousand miles in just a few nights.
几个晚上就可以飞出上千英里
How they know where and when to travel is a mystery,
它们如何确定出发时间以及目的地仍旧是个谜
but they all end up in one place - Kasanka, a remote swamp in Zambia.
但它们都在同一地方落脚：卡桑卡，赞比亚的一个偏远沼泽
There are ten million of them here.
这里约有一千万只蝙蝠
They crowd together in just one small patch of forest,
它们在差不多有两三个足球场大的
no bigger than two or three football pitches.
一小片丛林里聚集
And here they take up residence for a few weeks.
在此逗留几星期
It's the largest fruit bat roost on Earth.
这里成了地球上最大的食果蝙蝠栖息地
After their long journey,they need to rest and relax.
经过长途跋涉，它们需要休息
The roost is so crowded that complete strangers rub shoulders,
这里实在太挤，几乎肩靠着肩
and even snuggle up together.
甚至互相抱成一团
As evening approaches,
夜幕降临
they prepare to reap the reward for their long journey.
它们准备享用长途旅行的奖赏
They've come from all over Central Africa to this one place,
它们越过中非来到这里
because here,
因为
at this time of the year,
在每年此时
there is an extraordinary glut of mangoes and other fruit.
这里的芒果，还有其它果实正好丰收
Streaming out from the roost,they set off to collect it.
它们如潮水般涌出，去搜集食物
Each bat guzzles at least two kilos' worth of fruit every night.
每只蝙蝠一晚上，可以狂吞约两公斤的水果
In just a few weeks, this mega-roost
几周下来，这一群
will devour more than a billion separate fruits.
将会吃下多达十亿只水果
It's only the power of flight that allows these mammals
也只因具备飞行的能力，它们才能
to travel so far and so fast that they can reap such a brief harvest.
如此千里迢迢赶来，大吃一顿
After six weeks, the trees have been stripped of their fruit.
六周过后，树上的果子被吃个精光
Then, once again, the immense aerial armada takes to the air,
然后，这支庞大的空军又起飞
each bat returning to its own particular patch
各自回到原来
of the vast Congo forests.
位于刚果丛林的栖息地
The land mammals of Africa
非洲的陆生哺乳动物
also travel together in stupendous numbers.
也进行大规模的迁徙
The herds that graze the East African plains
东非草原上的动物数量
are not nearly the size they were a century ago,
比一个世纪前要少了很多
but they are still immense.
但仍旧很庞大
Grazing together is a good defence.
聚在一起是很好的防御策略
There's safety in numbers.
以数量取胜
But hunting together also brings advantages.
集体捕猎也会带来好处
This hyena, however,is searching for food on her own.
这只鬣狗，却在独自觅食
She needs to be careful.
它得小心
But she smells food.
但是它闻到了食物的味道
And she takes risks.
决定冒险
Bruised and bloodied, she is lucky to have survived her mistake.
皮开肉绽，它很幸运地在犯错后活了下来
But she's not totally defeated -
但它并没有被完全打败
she belongs to a clan.
它是一个家族的成员
A call to arms rings out through the night.
夜间，战斗的嚎叫响彻四方
Reinforcements assemble.
集结号
Every adult in the clan responds.
家族里成年的个体作出回应
If a clan attack together, they have a chance of challenging the lions.
如果一个家族一起攻击，它们可以挑战那几头狮子
It's a clan against a pride,each at full strength.
一群鬣狗挑战一个狮群，双方都全力以赴
And the clan outnumbers the pride.
鬣狗数量上占优势
The combined power of the hyenas
鬣狗们的强势
eventually forces the lions to retreat.
最终逼得狮子们撤退
Attacking as a coherent team
有组织地进行团队作战
requires a high degree of social cooperation,
需要高度的社会合作能力
and that is another of the mammals' specialities.
这也是哺乳动物的另一专长
Social bonds between mammals begin
动物间的联系
when mothers feed their young on milk.
在母亲哺育后代时就开始建立
And few look after their young with greater care
加上对幼小后代极好的照顾
than the mammal which dominates this landscape.
哺乳动物统治了自然
A female polar bear is trying to find food for her cubs.
一头母北极熊设正法为幼仔找食物
But this is a particularly
但这是一年中
difficult time of the year.
特别艰难的时日
The sea ice on which she hunts is melting beneath her feet.
供觅食的冰面正在开始融化
She must look for food on land.
它必须上岸
They're all safely ashore, but they could still face months of hunger.
它们都安全上岸，但还需面临几个月的饥荒
Finding food is not so easy on this cold and barren coast.
在这寒冷贫瘠的海岸，寻找食物实在太难
The search may be a long one.
搜寻过程很漫长
Polar bears have an extraordinarily sensitive sense of smell.
北极熊有着异常敏锐的嗅觉
And she has caught a faint whiff of something promising.
它嗅到了一丝希望
It's the immense carcass of a bowhead whale.
是一具巨大的北极露脊鲸的尸体
A whale carcass could provide more than any one family could eat.
这具尸体可供这一家子吃好长时间
But they're not the first here to find it...
但毕竟不是它们
by any means.
最先发现的
The smell has brought in bears from miles away.
气味将远处的熊都引来了
Bear families seldom get on with one another.
北极熊一家很少与另一家相处
She's taking a risk bringing her cubs here.
所以，带小熊来这里很冒险
Male bears can, and do,kill and eat small cubs.
公熊可能，也确实会杀死，吃掉小熊
Another family challenges her.
另一家向它挑战
She must decide whether to compete for food, or run away and go hungry.
它必须决定，是继续争夺食物 还是带着孩子逃跑，然后挨饿
She keeps her cubs close to her and stands her ground.
它将幼仔护在自己身边，守住地盘
Their mother's courage has won the cubs a meal.
母亲的勇气为孩子挣来一餐
Living as a family may bring rewards,
群居生活可以带来回报
but it can also create problems, for siblings can also become rivals.
但也会带来麻烦，因为兄弟姐妹之间会竞争
A coati - a South American relative of the racoon.
南美长鼻浣熊
These babies were born in a nest high in a tree,
这些小家伙是在树上的窝里出生的
and are about to come down to the ground for the first time.
现在第一次下地
Some more reluctantly than others.
有些很排斥其它的浣熊
Once on the ground, the mother coati rounds her babies up
一旦到了地面，母亲会把小仔们聚在一起
and takes them away to join a single large group.
形成一个大的群体
Together, these families form a gang up to 40 strong.
一个家庭有40多个成员
Once again, numbers bring safety.
数量多就安全
The first to spot danger will warn everyone.
最先觉察到危险的会警告所有的
But keeping order isn't easy,
但维持秩序就不容易了
and when they find food,it's a free-for-all.
一旦发现食物，熊熊有份
Meerkats in the Kalahari Desert
卡拉哈利沙漠的猫鼬
also live in large groups,but they are rather more organised.
也是群体生活，但它们更有组织性
Each family band is controlled by a queen,
每个家族被一位年长雌性所掌控
who is nearly always the only female to breed.
几乎是唯一的有生育能力的
She has been kept very busy suckling her five pups,
它一直忙碌于哺育5个小仔
and it's high time they became more independent.
它们是时候该独立自主了
Today is the new brood's first trip to get breakfast for themselves.
今天是这些新生儿第一次自己找早餐
It takes weeks for youngsters to learn how to find food.
新手们要花好几周学习如何找食物
This one is trying to catch ants,
这个家伙试图抓蚂蚁
but hasn't quite grasped the necessary technique.
但还没掌握必需的技巧
But this youngster has persuaded an adult to show him what to do.
但这个小家伙说服了一个年长的，示范该怎么做
The tutor is not his parent,just an enthusiastic instructor,
导师并不是父母，只是有了热情
and one who will adapt his lessons to the ability of his student.
通过教学将能力传给学生
This new one is a beginner,
这个是初学者
so he starts with something easy -how to dig for insect larvae.
所以从简单的开始，如何挖出一只昆虫幼虫
Other meals, like this one,are much trickier.
另一位，如这个，则棘手的多
So the tutor disables the scorpion's sting
老师在让它对付蝎子之前
before he lets the youngster tackle it.
会先搞定它的毒刺
The family also cooperates in defence.
家族也会协同防御
Every member does a tour of guard duty, keeping an eye out for danger.
每一位都会轮流站岗，留心危险
So, while one watches,
所以，只要有一只放哨
everyone else can rest.
其它的都可以放松
And, on warm days,one can easily nod off.
在大热天里，很容易打盹
The secret of meerkats' success
猫鼬的成功奥秘在于
is that everyone takes a turn in communal duties.
每一位都轮流站岗
But many mammals do more than just share their workload.
许多哺乳类不止是分担工作量
Some can share their knowledge, and do so across several generations.
还可以通过好几代来分享智慧
Elephant survival depends on profiting
大象的生存得益于
from the experience of many lifetimes.
好多代传下来的经验
This baby elephant was born last night,
这只小象是昨晚才出生的
and the whole herd seems to welcome this new addition.
整个家族都很欢迎它的加入
But the mother is young and inexperienced.
但这位母亲很年轻，经验不足
This is her first baby.
这是它第一个孩子
If she is to produce milk,a mother must drink.
母亲必须喝水，才能产奶
And the newborn calf must keep up with her
新生儿则要跟着它
as the herd continues on their long journey to find water.
象群走上了寻找水源的路
After five miles,the calf is flagging.
走了五英里，小象很疲惫
Enough is enough.
走够了
The young mother encourages her calf to continue,
年轻的母亲鼓励它继续
but there is still a long way to go,
但前路仍旧漫长
and the calf is already getting dehydrated.
小象已经开始脱水
The elephants are now so close to water that they can smell it.
现在象群已经离水不远了，可以嗅到水的味道
Water, at last.
终于到了
This is the calf's first encounter with a waterhole.
这是小象第一次遇到水坑
She's not sure what to make of it or, indeed, how to get out of it.
它不确定是怎么回事，也不知道怎么爬出来
Her mother tries to help her,
母亲试图帮助它
but she has no experience of dealing with babies.
但它没有带孩子的经验
BABY ELEPHANT CRIES OUT
（小象哭喊）
As the herd moves deeper into the swamp, the calf follows,
小象跟着象群朝沼泽深处前进
but now she is in real trouble.
现在，它真的麻烦大了
BABY ELEPHANT CRIES OUT
（小象哭喊）
Elephant babies can, and do, get permanently stuck in deep mud.
小象有可能会永远地陷入泥潭
Her mother's attempts to help her baby are only making matters worse.
母亲试图帮助它，但只会越帮越糟糕
It's stuck beneath her and she's pushing it deeper still.
会让它越陷越深
But now the baby's grandmother spots the problem and steps in.
这时孩子的祖母发现了问题，走了过来
Drastic action!She pushes mother out of the way
直截了当,它用象牙在后面戳了一下
with an unceremonious poke in the rump,
将孩子妈妈推向一边
and enables her granddaughter to scramble free.
使得它的孙子能够爬出来
Mother and calf have learned a valuable lesson from grandma.
母亲和小孩从祖母那里学来重要一课
Such passing of wisdom across generations
智慧像这样代代相传
has been an important element in the survival of elephants.
是大象能够生存的重要基础
The largest animal on land,the elephant is a mammal.
最大的陆生动物大象，是哺乳类
And so are the largest animals in the sea.
海洋里最大的动物也同样是哺乳类
A female humpback whale and her calf.
雌性驼背鲸和它的孩子
Every few years,she will travel 3,000 miles,
每隔几年，它都会游过3000英里
from the rich waters of the Antarctic
从南极富饶的水域
to these warm, but comparatively sterile, waters of the Pacific
到太平洋的温暖但是食物稀少的地区
to give birth to a single calf.
产下一只幼仔
The seas around Tonga are not only a nursery for humpbacks,
汤加周围的海域，不止是驼背鲸的育儿所
but also their mating ground.
也是它们的交配场所
This 50-year-old female has come here to seek the best partner,
这头50岁的母鲸来这里，寻找最佳配偶
and she starts by announcing her arrival to potential suitors.
它开始对潜在的追求者宣告自己的到来
One by one, the males arrive.
异性一个个到来
But as they do, she swims away,
但它却游走了
compelling her half a dozen or so suitors to follow her.
使得六头追随者跟着
She leads, while the males jockey for position behind her.
它领头，雄性们则在后面抢位置
The males bellow threats to one another,
雄性们互相吼叫着示威
creating huge plumes of bubbles.
弄出巨大的水花
So far, it has been a relatively gentle affair.
直到现在，一切还算公平、缓和
Now the competition becomes serious.
眼下竞争变得严峻
Hour after hour, the males battle for position, right behind her.
一小时一小时过去，雄性在它后面抢位置
And now the 40-tonne males begin to smash into one another.
40多吨重的鲸们开始互相撞击
This is the most massive battle in all nature.
这是自然界最大块头的战斗
Rival males can kill one another.
它们可以使对手致死
As the conflict reaches its climax,
在战斗最为激烈时
they try to force each other downwards.
它们希望对手都屈服
At last, a victor takes his place alongside the female
最后，胜者将会陪伴在母鲸身边
and remains unchallenged.
不会再有不服
By inciting the males to fight,
通过诱使雄性们决斗
the female has secured the best mate for herself -
母鲸可以确保找到最佳的伴侣
the one who is most likely to father the strongest offspring.
从而能够产下最强的后代
Together,the couple dive to the depths.
夫妻双双潜入深处
But still,no-one knows where they will mate.
但直到现在也没人知道它们在哪里交配
All mammals, including ourselves,
所有哺乳动物，包括我们
share a set of winning characteristics.
都有一系列领先的特征
Warm bodies, extraordinary senses and highly-developed intelligence -
恒温的身体、敏锐的感官和高度发达的智力
and those qualities have contributed to their, and our, success.
这些特质帮助它们，和我们，成功
But perhaps the most important characteristic of all
也许，所有特征里最重要的
lies in the strength of our family ties.
是来自我们的家庭力量
It is the mammal family that has conquered the earth.
哺乳动物是以家族的方式占领地球的
Tonga is famous for humpback whales,
汤加，以驼背鲸闻名
but even here, finding and filming whales in the open ocean
但即便在这儿，想找到并拍摄鲸
would prove challenging.
也是不小的挑战
For the Life team,
Life摄制组想要
capturing the humpback whales'unique mating contest,
拍到驼背鲸独特而著名的
known as a heat run,
求爱竞赛
would need local knowledge, hours on the water, and a big slice of luck.
需要花大量时间、当地的知识和超好的运气
We've heard that one of the boats further inland
我们听说靠近陆地的一只船
has seen a female with a calf and an escort,
见过一头带幼仔的母鲸和一批追随者
which is something which might build to, hopefully, a heat run,
这极有可能处于发情期
so we're gonna head over there and take a look.
所以我们朝那边赶，去看看
Any adult female with a calf could be coming into season,
任何一头带小孩的母鲸都有可能出镜
and so might be a target for amorous males.
还会是发情的公鲸们的目标
When we got there, I was pretty excited,
到那里时，我非常兴奋
a little bit nervous,didn't know what to expect.
也有点紧张，不知道会发生什么
Once I got in the water and dived down,
一旦我潜到水里
it was surprisingly quiet and mellow.
一片安静祥和
Certainly didn't expect what happened next.
当然没预料到接下来的事
The calf just came straight up towards me.
那头小鲸直接冲我而来
She seemed really relaxed, and definitely interested in me.
它看上去很放松，对我很有兴趣
It's literally just swimming around within metres of them,
就在我周围几米处游动，轻轻摇尾巴
flicking its tail,just being inquisitive I think,
我想，它应该很好奇吧
and having a bit of fun.
也有点好玩
It's obviously quite young,
确实还很小
so it's staying on the surface quite a long time.
所以在水面呆的时间很长
It's not diving down for very long,
不能下潜很久
maybe a couple of minutes.The mother will be
大概几分钟吧，它母亲
about five or ten metres below just keeping an eye on it.
会在下面5到10米处看守着
But even a calf has great power in its fins and tail.
但即便是幼鲸，鳍和尾巴仍旧力量十足
Roger will need to be careful.
Roger需要小心为妙
Got it?
接着
That was the most silly thing I've ever seen in my life.
这是我见过的最荒诞的事情
It was just gambolling around like a little newborn lamb.
它在周围玩耍，就像新生羔羊
But it's two tonnes.
但它有两吨重啊
Couple of bumps as it's come round, splashed his fluke at me or whatever.
它朝我搅了些水流什么的
I got a great shot of it, Jason.
Jason，我拍到了一些画面
Jason was backpedalling like this!
Jason后仰成这样了
It's just a baby.Like a little puppy,
只是头幼鲸，还小呢
you're playing with a little puppy, but it's four metres long.
你在和一个小动物玩，但是有四米长
It's just ludicrous.Was his mum all right?
很荒谬吧，它妈妈怎么样？
She is just totally chilling out underneath.
它在下面怪吓人的
Pecs back. Just hanging like this at about 15 metres.
在水下15米处像这样悬停着
Yeah, just hanging there.
是的，只是悬在那里
Probably didn't even see it,I don't think.
或许是没看见，但我不这么认为
It's one thing to be close to a playful baby.
和贪玩的小鲸一起是一回事儿
It will be another to be in the path
但和一群雄激素水平超高的
of a testosterone-charged group of males,
体型是它十倍的雄性鲸
each ten times her size.
是另一回事
There are enough males here for a heat run, but are they in the mood?
这里有很多雄性鲸，但它们发情了吗？
That was pretty good.
真不错
When you guys are ready.
你们准备好了吗
Quick as you can.
越快越好
These whales can weigh up to 40 tonnes and move surprisingly quickly.
这些鲸体重可达40吨，而且速度奇快
As well as getting the camera to get the shots -
摄影机拍到好的画面
they have to be fairly close -
得跟它们足够接近
we have to be careful they don't get bumped.
我们必须小心，不要被撞到
If they get a knock from one of these guys,
如果被它们撞一下
it could do some serious damage.
会造成严重的损害
He's right towards you.
它朝你过来了
To avoid disturbing the whales' behaviour,
为了不影响鲸的行为
the team need to free-dive,without scuba tanks,
组员们必须自由潜水，不带呼吸器
holding their breath as long as they can.
尽可能地憋气
On a good dive, I can hold my breath for maybe two minutes.
状态好的话，我可以憋气两分钟
These guys,they can go for 20 minutes or more
但这些家伙，可以憋住20多分钟
before they have to come up for air.
然后再到水面换气
There's no contest.
没法比
More and more whales are gathering,
越来越多的鲸聚集过来
but it's not turning into a heat run yet.
但还没有达到发情状态
Hard to say what's going on.
很难说发生了什么
Were there five that time?
是不是有5头？
They're kind of moving around,coming up and under and over.
它们只是游来游去，忽上忽下
Hopefully,something's starting to happen.
可望有事发生
Maybe love's in the air?
莫非爱情在空中？
Love may be in the air,but it isn't in the water.
爱情也许是在空中，但水里是没有的
Despite keeping tabs on the whales over the next ten days,
接下来十天里，尽管一直跟着这些鲸
there was still no sign of a heat run starting.
但仍旧不见它们发情的迹象
You'd think it'd be quite easy to keep track of a 40-tonne animal.
你也许会认为，跟踪这些40多吨的家伙很容易
And we've got six of them out here,
我们一路跟着六头过来
and we keep losing them.One minute they're there,
不断地跟丢，一分钟前它们还在这里
we get up reasonably close,
然后我们靠近
and within 30 seconds, they've dived and they're gone again.
不到半分钟，它们又潜下去，失踪了
And then it takes another maybe five minutes, ten minutes,
然后，再等五到十分钟
and then they'll come up again and they'll be 300 yards away,
它们会在300多码外又再次出现
and it takes ages just to get close to them.
然后又得花很长时间跟进
So we're just playing a continuous game of cat and mouse.
一直跟我们在玩猫捉老鼠的游戏
Cat and mouse? It's whales.
猫和老鼠？它们是鲸鱼哦
The mating season is coming to an end,
眼看繁殖季节就要结束了
and the crew haven't completed their mission.
制作组还没完成拍摄任务呢
But then, at last, the whales' behaviour seems to have changed.
最后，那些鲸的行为看起来有变化
Well, this is it!
好，这就是了
We just spotted about six or seven humpbacks on the horizon.
我们在远处地平线发现了六到七头鲸
We think it's a heat run.
我们认为那就是求爱竞赛
The last 16, 17 days on the water
在水上的最后16、17天
are probably gonna come down to the next two hours,
取决于接下来两小时
as to whether we get our shots or not.
我们能否拍到画面
The chase is on!
追逐开始了
There was at least three or four males going past -
至少有三、四头鲸游过
they were competing and knocking into each other
它们互相争斗、互相撞击
as they tried to get the poll position behind the female.
尽力抢得母鲸后面的位置
It's right at you,it's right at you.
朝你过来了，冲你过来了
The whales are moving so fast that, to stand any chance of filming them,
鲸游得太快了，想要找机会拍到它们
the crew needs to be dropped right in front of the charging group.
组员们必须在它们正前方入水
Just as Roger gets alongside the males,
正当Roger来到鲸的旁边
the tempo of the chase suddenly shifts to full bore
拍摄追逐的画面，忽然被
with a flick of a tail.
一个摆尾扰乱
Facing the charging males deep underwater, Roger keeps shooting,
面对发情的雄鲸，Roger在水下持续拍摄
holding his breath until the group pass over.
屏住呼吸直到它们游过
A quick gasp of air, and Roger's back down again.
然后迅速上来换口气，又继续下水
The whales continue to rush by.
鲸们鱼贯而过
In the end,Roger just can't keep up any longer.
最后，Roger实在是憋不住了
Exhausted, it's time to return to the boat for the last time.
精疲力竭，他们最后一次回到了船上
Amazing! That was the most amazing experience I've ever had.
惊奇！实在是我最惊讶的一次经历
There was about...
大约有
seven or eight. Both dived down about 20 metres in front.
七到八头鲸，在前面水下20米左右
And then the female came through first, quite close.
雌性先游过来，很近
And then they all just started diving towards me,
然后它们都一下子朝我冲过来
it was like standing in a stream of traffic.
就像面对着车流一样
It was just one one side, one the next side, one the next side.
这边一头，这边一头，另一边也有
And then, after about 40 seconds,
再过了约40秒
40, 45 seconds, I was getting a little bit out of breath.
45秒的样子，我有点透不过气来
And then I looked up, and there's one sitting right on top of me.
我向上看，头顶上还有一头
Did you get it? I think so. Hope so.
你拍到了吗？我想是的
If not, then we're both fired!
如果没有，我们都会被炒鱿鱼的
It's taken 18 days and hundreds of dives,
花了18天，几百次潜水
but at last the team have been able to reveal a secret
最终，摄制组能够拍到
of these whales' lives that few people have ever seen.
鲜为人知的鲸鱼的秘密